<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of advice to the churches of the non-conformists in the English nation endeavouring their satisfaction in that point, who are the true Church of England?</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50136</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12924510</idno>
  <idno type="VID">95457</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264186826</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1119</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8763</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12924510</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50136)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95457)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 988:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of advice to the churches of the non-conformists in the English nation endeavouring their satisfaction in that point, who are the true Church of England?</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and sold by A. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Cotton Mather. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Philalethes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Freedom of religion --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95457:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95457:1"/>
            <p>A Letter of Advice TO THE CHURCHES OF THE Non-conformists IN THE <hi>English Nation:</hi> Endeavouring their Satisfaction in that POINT, <hi>Who are the True Church of</hi> England?</p>
            <q>
               <p>There was a Strife between the Herdmen of Abraham's Cattel, and the Herdmen of Lot's Cattel: and the Canaanite and the Perizzite were yet in the Land, <bibl>
                     <hi>Gen. 13.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Fortasse &amp; in hoc Loco, imperita praevaluit Consuetudo; &amp; aliquid afferri potest, quod adhuc Ignoramus; unde nos magis docere debeat Judicium veritatis, quam praejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium Consuetudinis. <bibl>
                     <hi>Aug. in Ps. 105.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and Sold by <hi>A. Baldwin</hi> at the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:95457:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>There will speedily be Published,</hi> An Answer to Dr. <hi>Scott</hi>'s <hi>Cases of Conscience against the Dissenters,</hi> about <hi>Forms of Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sold by</hi> A. Baldwin.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:95457:2"/>
            <head>The Publisher to the READER.</head>
            <p>CHildren of Strife there are, who will be straitway saying of the Author of this Letter, as <hi>Ahab</hi> said of <hi>Ben-hadad; Mark and see, how this Man seeketh Mischief.</hi> But, it's agreed that thou thy self be judge what Mischief he seeketh, if thou canst first prevail with thy self to think as follows:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sick</hi> our Nation is; <hi>Heart-sick</hi> of Impiety against Heaven, and of Animosity against one another. <hi>Sick</hi> and incurable by the President and whole Colledge of our Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicians, King, and Parliament. <hi>Sick, and more like to die than live,</hi> unless <hi>Vixons</hi> do take better ways to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, than <hi>gnawing their Tongues, and refusing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; fretting against their God, and their King,</hi> and every thing but Themselves. In a word, Ʋnless the <hi>CHURCH</hi> (as we must still speak) do revert to her old Orthodoxy, the <hi>DISSENTERS</hi> to their old Purity, and <hi>BOTH</hi> of 'em to the religious Love of their Saviour, and of one another. If this may not be, <hi>the Fire will devour the great Deep;</hi> Contention will destroy our popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Countrey, <hi>Amos 7.4.</hi> Indeed,</p>
            <p>Our State on this Earth is one, but <hi>Weak,</hi> and <hi>Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> Religion, as all other Sciences, hath it's Problems and Abstrusities. Our <hi>Bernards</hi> see not all things. Yea, and the most of good and honest Hearts are Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sighted, and cannot see to the Well's bottom. No, and (what is much worse,) it is to be said of the most Intelligent, and Devout too, <hi>All mind their own things:</hi> Are too too much swayed by Domestick Interests; insomuch, that <hi>Peter</hi>'s and <hi>Paul</hi>'s will clash. The best of <hi>Viators</hi> will
<pb facs="tcp:95457:3"/>
               <hi>fall out by the way. Offences</hi> will come. And Earth will, never while it stands, be quite so kind and quiet as Heaven. But,</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding this, <hi>Peace must be followed.</hi> Peace with Truth, and for the sake of Truth. Necessity is laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; necessity of <hi>Precept</hi> and <hi>Means.</hi> Nor want we Encouragement: For our Saviour hath <hi>Bought</hi> it, <hi>Prays</hi> for it, and <hi>Promises</hi> it. Yes, and makes it easily attaina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by all good People, tho' of different Persuasions. It's not more easie for our Eyes, and Hands, and Feet, to keep from <hi>Mutiny,</hi> than for real Christians to have <hi>Peace</hi> among Themselves. Because, as they are Members of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, so are Christ's Servants: Members of one another in his one <hi>Mystical Body,</hi> and acted by one and the <hi>self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>same Spirit.</hi> So that an Arch-Bishop <hi>Usher,</hi> and a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian, Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> a Bishop <hi>Wilkins,</hi> and an Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Dr. <hi>Harrison,</hi> do naturally Love without Dissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, as naturally as the Sun does shine, or the Fire burn. Wherefore,</p>
            <p>The Learned and Holy Author of the following Pages, seeketh Truth and Peace: <hi>Forgive him this Wrong.</hi> It appears not what other Pardon he needs. His Style is formed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. As of Old <hi>Moses</hi> did, he laboureth to Quiet and Part fairly the Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Israelites;</hi> not offering to smite any but the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> and the <hi>most Merciless;</hi> and that but by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment neither. In short, it is engaged on his behalf, that he shall publickly Retract whatever Errour he shall be found to have erred. As far off as he stands, there are some who hear him saying, (as the grand Exemplar of Patience said unto the <hi>Temanite,) Teach me, and I will hold my Peace! Cause me to know wherein I have Erred.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95457:3"/>
            <head>A LETTER of Advice TO THE Churches of the Non-conformists IN THE <hi>English Nation,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Brethren in our Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen the Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was offended at the Great <hi>Ramus,</hi> who had been <hi>his Favourite,</hi> for becoming a <hi>Protestant,</hi> this Great <hi>Martyr</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured him, that he had been infinitely beholden to his <hi>Eminence,</hi> the <hi>Cardinal</hi> himself, in that from <hi>him</hi> he had learned the very <hi>Principle</hi> upon which it was that he became a <hi>Protestant;</hi> even <hi>this,</hi> That of the <hi>Fifteen Ages,</hi> which had ran out since the Ascension of our Saviour, the <hi>first</hi> was the <hi>Golden Age;</hi> and the rest grew still worse and worse, the remoter they were from <hi>That;</hi> wherefore, said he, <hi>Aureum seoulum delegi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same Consideration that made this Great Person be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>Protestant,</hi> hath produced the Churches of <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists,</hi> which have been <hi>sprinkled</hi> thro' the <hi>Realm</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Dominions</hi> thereto pertaining. He that would in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and the <hi>Discipline</hi> of the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a <hi>Conformity</hi> to the <hi>Golden Age</hi> of <hi>Christianity,</hi> must come to the Churches of <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> which have need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly been sometimes Distinguished into <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95457:4"/>
               <hi>Congregational,</hi> but are now, I hope, losing the Distinction, in that more <hi>Christian</hi> Name of <hi>United Brethren.</hi> While those things in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> whereunto you, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> are <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> were evidently introduced, after the <hi>Golden Age</hi> of <hi>Christianity</hi> (except so far as <hi>Golden Chalices</hi> could make one) was expired, and not until the <hi>Apostacy</hi> which the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of Christ <hi>expresly</hi> foretold, had begun very sensibly to operate; you may challenge all sincere Students in <hi>Antiquity,</hi> to mention so much as one thing ordinarily practised in your Churches, for which you have not the Countenance of the <hi>Earliest Antiquity.</hi> You need not have recourse to <hi>Eyndwood,</hi> and <hi>Gallic,</hi> or <hi>Spanish,</hi> or <hi>Saxon Councils,</hi> for the Explaining and Maintaining of the Things used among you: <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> and <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Justin Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> or, if you will. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> shall be your Defenders. Yet after all, I know that you are of the Opinion with the <hi>Ancient</hi> last mentioned, <hi>Consuetudo sine veritate est vetustas error is;</hi> and, that you will allow the Speech of the Great Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> to pass for a true Translation of <hi>Cyprian, Antiquity without Truth, is a Cypher without a Figure.</hi> That which indeed gives a <hi>Figure</hi> to your Churches, is this, That the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of Christ, speaking in the Oracle of the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> is the only <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> which 'tis your <hi>Profession</hi> and <hi>Endeavour</hi> to follow, in the regulating of all things among them. Yea, tho' 'twill doubtless be a fault in you, to think that your Churches are come to a <hi>ne plus ultra</hi> in <hi>Reformation,</hi> and that their <hi>Works are perfect before God,</hi> yet there is in them that <hi>Conformity</hi> to the Directions of the Son of God in his Word, which has caused a <hi>Considerable</hi> Person,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Slings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Bethel,</hi> Esq;</note> among the <hi>Conformable</hi> Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> thus to express himself, (in his Judicious Book about <hi>The Interest of the Princes and States of</hi> Europe) That, <hi>should the Nation be at once empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of one whole Generation of Non-conformists, so long as the reading of the Bible is suffered, another will Unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and Immediately spring up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now albeit these two Considerations may be enough to fortifie you against all Discouragements in those <hi>Methods of Christianity,</hi> which you have espoused; and while you have the <hi>Word of Christ,</hi> with the purest of <hi>Christian Antiquity</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95457:4"/>Harmonizing to it on your side, you need not be any more moved, than a Church <hi>fair as the Moon,</hi> from keeping the <hi>Ordinances of Heaven,</hi> by unreasonable Noise and Clamour; nevertheless I know there is one <hi>Cry,</hi> whereby some of you are sometimes Discouraged.</p>
            <p>You have a Just Veneration for that Venerable Name, THE CHURCH OF <hi>ENGLAND;</hi> and a certain Party of Men, in the <hi>English Nation,</hi> unjustly <hi>Monopolizing</hi> that Name unto themselves, try to perswade you, that you are no part of the CHURCH OF <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> but miserable <hi>Schismaticks;</hi> yea, and it is well if you can escape the Fate of <hi>Infidels,</hi> when once that scandalous piece of <hi>Bigotry,</hi> late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advanced, shall obtain, <hi>That where there is no Episcopal Ordination, there is no true Church Minister, Sacrament, or Salvation.</hi> If then you may be perswaded and convinced, that you are a true Part of the CHURCH OF <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> and as Genuine <hi>Sons of the Church,</hi> as any that call her <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> it may be hoped not only that you will be established in the <hi>Course of Religion,</hi> which you now embrace, but also that the Prejudices of your <hi>Angry Brethren,</hi> whereby you have been sometimes opposed, will be happily extinguished.</p>
            <p>I am now therefore to undertake your Satisfaction in that Point, which I find particularly the Famous <hi>Baxter</hi> in his Treatise of <hi>National Churches,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 7. § 10.</note> expressing in these words:
<q rend="margQuotes">The present Orthodox Protestant <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> are as truely Members of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> justly so called, as any Diocesans or Conformists in the Land; and if they be not better confuted than hitherto they have been, they may truly be said to be the Soundest, most Judicious, most Conscionable, and the most Peaceable Members of this Church. And to deny such <hi>Non-conformists</hi> to be True and Honourable Parts of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> is but such an Effect of <hi>Ignorant Arrogance,</hi> as is the Shame of the Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and implieth some <hi>Dishonourable Definition</hi> of the said <hi>Church.</hi> And they that make their mutable <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> Essential to the Church, make a <hi>Ceremony</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> it self, and cannot answer the <hi>Papists,</hi> that Challenge us to prove its <hi>Antiquity;</hi> for our <hi>Liturgy</hi> is not so old as <hi>Luther</hi>'s Time; as <hi>Rome,</hi> by Claiming to be the <hi>Whole Church,</hi> hath made many think, 'tis not so much as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95457:5"/>a <hi>Part;</hi> so <hi>Conformists</hi> calling themselves the <hi>Whole Church of England,</hi> have tempted many to take them for no <hi>Part</hi> at all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And it will be strange if this be denied by any Man, that has heard of that ACT OF PARLIAMENT, by which you enjoy your present <hi>Liberty</hi> to Worship God according to <hi>his Directions,</hi> and your <hi>own Consciences.</hi> God, by a wondrous <hi>Revolution,</hi> brought unto the <hi>British Throne,</hi> a <hi>King</hi> and a <hi>Queen,</hi> who have signalized their Truly Royal Dispositions, to protect all Disciples of Christ, without regard unto <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Opinions</hi> in the <hi>Circumstantials</hi> of the <hi>Common Faith:</hi> An Illustrious KING, who hath on all Occasions discovered the Heroick Resolution, which on the greatest of Occasions he once expressed unto the <hi>Scotch</hi> Commissioners, <hi>Never to be a Persecutor:</hi> A Renowned QUEEN, who perpetually manifested such Princely Desires of <hi>Union</hi> among all Good Men of diverse Parties, as once particularly she uttered unto an Eminent Person, from whom I had it; <hi>In as much as a Man cannot make himself to believe what he will, why should we persecute one another? I wish I could see all Good Men of one Mind; but in the mean time I pray let them however Love one another.</hi> The Gracious God blessed the Nation at the same time with a <hi>Parliament,</hi> who understood and consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the <hi>Real Interest</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> in this respect. They considered, that the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> are a People of so great Account in the Nation for their <hi>Number,</hi> their <hi>Vertue,</hi> and their <hi>Trade,</hi> that it were a no less <hi>Foolish</hi> than <hi>Wicked</hi> thing, and all of a piece with the <hi>French Madness,</hi> to propound their <hi>Extirpation.</hi> They considered, that the <hi>Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists</hi> ever joined with the Sober Part of the <hi>Nation</hi> in the Defence of its <hi>Liberties,</hi> against the Encroachments of <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Government,</hi> while their <hi>worst Enemies</hi> were general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as <hi>bad Enemies</hi> to the <hi>English Liberties,</hi> and were the <hi>Men</hi> that stickled with might and main to introduce the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Tyranny,</hi> now so happily cast out. Their Majesties, (whose Royal Assent unto an Act for the utter Extirpation of <hi>Prelacy</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> hath restored <hi>Prosperity</hi> with <hi>Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> to that <hi>Kingdom</hi>) concurred with this Renowned Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in an <hi>Act of Induigence,</hi> by which the <hi>Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,</hi> who Subscribe the <hi>Doctrinal Articles</hi> of the <hi>Church
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95457:5"/>of</hi> England, are as much <hi>allowed,</hi> (tho' there be not so much <hi>allow'd</hi> unto <hi>them!</hi>) as those that conform to all the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> yet wanting a <hi>Reformation</hi> in it. Wherefore by <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> your <hi>Churches</hi> are now as <hi>legal Parts</hi> of the <hi>Church of</hi> England, as if you all used the invented Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Cross,</hi> or bow'd at the Name of <hi>Jesus.</hi> 'Tis true, the <hi>Ecclesiastical Benefices</hi> are still engrossed by the more <hi>Conformable</hi> and <hi>Ceremonious</hi> Clergy; and let a Man be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so <hi>Learned,</hi> never so <hi>Loyal,</hi> and never so capable of ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>King</hi> or the <hi>Church,</hi> yet, except he will engage to serve the <hi>Mitre,</hi> he is not thought worthy of any <hi>Preserment,</hi> or <hi>Employment;</hi> nevertheless the <hi>Law of</hi> England, which is all that has given the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> its <hi>political Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution,</hi> has also made <hi>you</hi> the <hi>True Members</hi> of it: And His Majesty, who is the <hi>Supream Head</hi> and <hi>Governour of the Church of</hi> England, hath declared you to be such <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of it, as are worthy of His Royal <hi>Protection:</hi> Yea, by <hi>Law,</hi> your Churches are not only <hi>protected</hi> with a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty on all that shall give you <hi>open Disturbances,</hi> but <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded</hi> also with the Exemption of <hi>your</hi> Ministers from <hi>civil Encumbrances.</hi> But if this happy <hi>Revolution</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver happened, yet so long as the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> will by reasonable Men, be reckon'd no other than the <hi>Body of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian People in</hi> England, I hope none will deny <hi>you</hi> to be <hi>part</hi> of that Church; for, I am sure, none can deny <hi>you</hi> to be as much a <hi>Christian People</hi> as any upon that Island. The Monsters of late so horribly multiplied, who Deride, and Blaspheme, and Cast off the holy <hi>Religion</hi> of CHRIST, are not of <hi>your Communion.</hi> And, besides all this, if the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> confess, and assert <hi>yours</hi> to be <hi>True Churches</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, I do not see how it can question your being <hi>true Parts</hi> of it self. It will not be for the Honour of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that it should be said, There is a <hi>Visible Church of Christ</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> which is no Part of it. Now the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> has given us this for the <hi>Nineteenth</hi> of its famous <hi>Thirty Nine</hi> Articles: <hi>The Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible Church of Christ is a Congregation of faithful Men, in which the pure Word of God is preached, and the Sacraments be duly ministred according to Christ's Ordinance in all those things, that of necessity are requisite to the same:</hi> And that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95457:6"/>the <hi>pure Word of God is preached,</hi> and the <hi>Sacraments ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred with all that is of necessity requisite unto them</hi> in your <hi>Congregations,</hi> I suppose 'tis incontestable. That Man who denies it, must be far gone in <hi>Bigotry</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that you may more particularly apprehend your Claim to be the very CHURCH OF <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> I will in seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Particulars describe to you the <hi>True Church of</hi> England, and make it evident, that those things wherein you are <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters,</hi> are maintained rather by a <hi>New Church,</hi> (and I had almost used a harder word) than by that, which the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Name of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> originally belongs unto.</p>
            <p>We will begin, as 'tis fitting we should make our Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, with the DOCTRINE of the <hi>Church.</hi> 'Tis most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in its <hi>Thirty Nine Articles,</hi> is that which a great Part of the Clergy, now engrosing the Name of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> explode the literal sense of. There are certain glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Truths</hi> held by the <hi>True Church of</hi> England. <hi>e. g.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="article" n="17">
                        <head>ART. 17.</head>
                        <p>
                           <q rend="margQuotes">
                              <hi>Predestination</hi> to Life, is the everlasting purpose of God, whereby (before the Foundations of the World were laid) he hath constantly decreed by his Counsel, secret to us, to deliver from Curse and Damnation those whom he hath chosen in Christ out of Mankind, and to bring them by Christ to everlasting Salvation, as Vessels made to Honour. Wherefore they that be endued with so excellent a Benefit of God, be called according to God's purpose by his Spirit, working in due season; they thro' Grace obey the Calling; they be justified freely; they be made the Sons of God by Adoption; they be made like the Image of his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son Jesus Christ; they walk religiously in good Works; and at length by God's Mercy, they attain to everlasting Felicity. The godly consideration of <hi>Predestination,</hi> and our <hi>Election</hi> in Christ, is full of sweet, pleasant, and unspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able comfort to godly Persons.</q>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95457:6"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="article" n="18">
                        <head>ART. 18.</head>
                        <p>
                           <q rend="margQuotes">They are to be had <hi>Accursed,</hi> that presume to say, That every Man shall be saved by the Law or Sect which he professeth, so that he be diligent to frame his Life accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that Law, and the Light of Nature; for holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture doth set out unto us only the Name of Jesus Christ whereby Men must be saved.</q>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="article" n="10">
                        <head>ART. 10.</head>
                        <p>
                           <q rend="margQuotes">The Condition of Man after the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> is such, as that he cannot turn and prepare himself by his own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Strength, and good Works, to Faith and Calling upon God. Wherefore we have no power to do good Works pleasant and acceptable to God, without the Grace of God by Christ preventing us, that we may have a good Will, and working with us when we have that good Will.</q>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="article" n="11">
                        <head>ART. 11.</head>
                        <p>
                           <q rend="margQuotes">We are accounted <hi>Righteous</hi> before God, only for the Merit of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, by Faith, and not for our own Works and Deservings; wherefore that we are <hi>justified by Faith only,</hi> is a most wholesom Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and very full of Comfort.</q>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="article" n="13">
                        <head>ART. 13.</head>
                        <p>
                           <q rend="margQuotes">Works done before the Grace of Christ, and the Inspirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Spirit, are not pleasant to God, forasmuch as they spring not of Faith in Jesus Christ; neither do they make Men meet to receive Grace, or (as the School-Authors say) deserve <hi>Grace of Congruity;</hi> yea, rather for that they are not done as God hath willed and commanded them to be done, we doubt not but they have the Nature of <hi>Sin.</hi>
                           </q>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="article" n="29">
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95457:7"/>
                        <head>ART. 29.</head>
                        <p>
                           <q rend="margQuotes">The wicked, and such as be void of a lively Faith, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' they do carnally and visibly press with the Teeth, (as St. <hi>Augustine</hi> saith,) the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Christ; yet in no wise are they partakers of <hi>Christ,</hi> but rather to their Condemnation do <hi>eat</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> the Sign and Sacrament of so great a thing.</q>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Behold, Sirs, the <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>True Church of</hi> England! A <hi>Faith,</hi> which when it is betray'd by any <hi>Church, Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> it self is betray'd, and such a <hi>Church</hi> becoming <hi>offensive</hi> to the Almighty Lord Jesus Christ, cannot be far from <hi>Marks of his Displeasure set upon it.</hi> And, I am very sure, that this <hi>Faith</hi> is no where maintained with more <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Constancy</hi> than it is in the Churches of the <hi>Non-Conformists:</hi> Doubtless 'tis a <hi>Mystery</hi> unto <hi>you, my Brethren,</hi> to find these <hi>Articles</hi> commonly and publickly reviled with pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Confutations</hi> in the Writings of those very Men that have subscribed these <hi>Articles;</hi> and being by their <hi>subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption</hi> qualified for <hi>Benefices,</hi> run away with the Name of the only <hi>Church of</hi> England. Your <hi>Simplicity,</hi> doubtless, cannot comprehend this <hi>Mystery,</hi> that the Men who have <hi>subscribed</hi> these very <hi>Articles,</hi> can in defiance of their <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription,</hi> write and rail against them, and be for <hi>that very Cause,</hi> counted worthy of the best <hi>Preferments</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> when <hi>you</hi> that <hi>contend earnestly for them,</hi> are made utterly uncapable of the least <hi>Imployments,</hi> meerly because you scruple some <hi>Invented Rituals.</hi> I would put it unto the Consciences of some thousands that now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the <hi>Ecclesiastical Benefices,</hi> whether they would not make a <hi>Tragical out-cry</hi> upon it, if they were deprived of their <hi>Benefices,</hi> and shut out of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the <hi>Non-Conformity</hi> of their Judgments to the <hi>Faith of the Church,</hi> in the <hi>Five Points</hi> of the Doctrine of <hi>Grace?</hi> I will not now bestow upon those <hi>Pelagian Enemies</hi> to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Brand that justly belongs unto them, for the <hi>Dissimulation</hi> with which they have <hi>subscribed</hi> these <hi>Articles</hi> of the Church; albeit, for Men to <hi>subscribe</hi> these <hi>Articles,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95457:7"/>and they to make this Apology for their denying and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of them, <hi>That they subscribed them not as Articles of Faith, but as Articles of Peace;</hi> many will tell you, it must be with an <hi>Equivocation,</hi> than which no <hi>Jesuit</hi> can use a greater: And some will enquire, Whether in <hi>Asia</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> a Man might not with as much Honesty <hi>subscribe</hi> the <hi>Alcoran?</hi> Which I the rather mention, because it begins to be published, (not by any of <hi>your</hi> Communion,) That for to make a <hi>good Christian</hi> and a <hi>Member of the Church,</hi> there is required no more than that a Man believe <hi>Jesus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth to be the Messiah;</hi> and yet this is a thing many times over expresly acknowledged in the <hi>Alcoran.</hi> All that I will say, is, That while things continue thus, it will be impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to hinder Mankind from thinking, that a few <hi>invented Rituals,</hi> are with some of more value than all the glorious <hi>Doctrines of Grace,</hi> and those invaluable Treasures of <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Truth,</hi> which the <hi>Church of England</hi> is enriched withal. We will not now take the invidious Pains to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up the numberless Passages of <hi>Arminian</hi> Stuff, directly contrary to these <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> which occur in the <hi>Pamphlets</hi> of the Divines, that would be thought the only Darlings and Champions of the <hi>Church.</hi> But this is notorious to the World, that so far as a full <hi>Assent</hi> and <hi>Consent</hi> unto this <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> can make <hi>you</hi> so; (and I see not why it should <hi>not</hi> make you so;) you, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> are the most sincere <hi>Parts</hi> of that <hi>Church.</hi> Yea, in many places, and particularly where the Writer of this Letter lives, a Man cannot hear the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> preached, except he go to <hi>your Churches</hi> for it. And except some amazing Work of Heaven pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served no where but in <hi>your Churches;</hi> and I pray God, that at least it may be preserved <hi>There.</hi> The <hi>Old</hi> and the <hi>True Church of England,</hi> as it had the same Sentiment of <hi>Calvinism</hi> with <hi>you,</hi> so it honoured the Name of <hi>Calvin,</hi> as an <hi>excellent Instrument of God for the clearing and spread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Truth;</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">So Dr. <hi>Carlton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hakewel,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hoyl, &amp;c.</hi> in their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Writings.</note> and resented the Reproaches cast upon that <hi>Man of God,</hi> as thro' the sides of <hi>Calvin, striking at the Throat and Heart of our Religion.</hi> (Such are the Expressions in the Books Dedicated to K. <hi>James</hi> I.) And
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95457:8"/>you take the famous Dr. <hi>Du Moulin</hi> to be not a jot the less <hi>a Church of</hi> England <hi>Man,</hi> for going out of the World with that Lamentation, <hi>since</hi> Calvinism <hi>is decried in</hi> England, <hi>[Actum est de Religione Christi apud Anglos,] Christianity it self will be in danger to be lost in the</hi> English <hi>Nation.</hi> But the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> cannot be sincere Members of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> because they do not acknowledge the <hi>Divine Right</hi> of the Modern DIOCESAN EPISCOPACY. No! I pray, why not? Let us a little enquire into the Judgment of the <hi>Old</hi> and the <hi>True Church of England</hi> upon this matter, and it will presently appear, that <hi>you</hi> are far more of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> than those <hi>Fanaticks</hi> (of late so much increased,) that not only advance the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of their <hi>Diocesan Episcopacy,</hi> but also question the validity of the <hi>Sacraments</hi> administred by any that have not received their <hi>Ordination</hi> from it. Albeit the present <hi>Form of making and consecrating Bishops, Priests, and Deacons,</hi> asserts, That <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Priests</hi> are <hi>distinct Orders,</hi> and they must be published as <hi>Excommunicate,</hi> who affirm, <hi>That this Book does contain any thing in it repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Word of God:</hi> Yet, <hi>my Brethren, from the Beginning it was not so.</hi> Behold, <hi>The Church of England</hi> it self stands <hi>Excommunicate</hi> by its own <hi>Canons,</hi> as much as <hi>you.</hi> It is notorious, that the <hi>Diocesan Episcopacy</hi> and the National Church-Government by <hi>Dishops,</hi> was never own'd to be <hi>Jure Divino</hi> until K. <hi>James</hi> I. came to be King of <hi>England.</hi> It was <hi>he,</hi> who upon the Enchantments of <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft,</hi> first yielded unto <hi>that,</hi> which his Predecessors would never have endured.
<note n="(d)" place="margin">See this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Mr. <hi>Lobs</hi>'s <hi>True Dissenter,</hi> Chap. 1.</note> Even in King <hi>Elfrick</hi>'s days,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> p. 576 l. 17.</note> the <hi>Church of England</hi> plainly denied <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Priests</hi> to be <hi>distinct Orders.</hi> But I will not carry you back to such <hi>early Days.</hi> In the Days of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Tindal</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">In his <hi>Practice of Popish Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates.</hi>
               </note> expresly maintained,
<q rend="margQuotes">That the Apostles following the Rule of Christ, ordained in his Kingdom and Congregation <hi>Two Officers;</hi> one called <hi>Bishop,</hi> which same was called <hi>Priest</hi> and <hi>Elder;</hi> and another called <hi>Deacon.</hi> All that were called <hi>Elders</hi> or <hi>Priests</hi> (he says,) were called <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops</hi> also.</q> Thus wrote the <hi>Martyr</hi> who was own'd by his Enemies themselves, <hi>Homo doctus, pius, &amp; bonus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95457:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Lambert</hi> expresly maintained,
<note n="(g)" place="margin">In <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon.</hi> Vol. 2</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">That in the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church</hi> there were no more Officers than <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Deacons;</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> saith Those we call <hi>Priests</hi> are all one, and no other but <hi>Bishops,</hi> and the <hi>Bishops</hi> none other but <hi>Priests.</hi> One of the <hi>Articles</hi> against <hi>Barnes,</hi> was
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> his holding, That they who in one place are called <hi>Episcopi,</hi> or <hi>Bishops,</hi> you shall find in many that they be called <hi>Presbyteri,</hi> or <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> and that according to <hi>Athanasius,</hi> every City should have its <hi>proper Pastor;</hi> and according to <hi>Chrysostom,</hi> the Teachers were not to be distracted with the governing <hi>many Churches,</hi> but have the Care and Charge of <hi>one Church</hi> only.</q> And this Persuasion wherein <hi>you</hi> thus follow your Fathers, the Blessed <hi>Martyrs</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> at last prevailed so far, that <hi>Cranmer</hi> himself, with others, embraced it. Yea, 'twas not long before this became a Point established by Authority: and, in <hi>The necessary Erudition of a Christian Man,</hi> a Book then published by Authority, as the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> it is expresly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, <hi>That of these two Orders only</hi> [Priests and Deacons] <hi>Scripture makes express mention.</hi> The
<note n="(i)" place="margin">See the <hi>Adden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> to Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s <hi>History of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> p. 321.</note> Declaration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Institution of Bishops and Priests,</hi> then also sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed by the brave Lord <hi>Cromwel</hi> and the <hi>Archhishops</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> and other <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Civilians,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied any <hi>Superiority</hi> of a <hi>Bishop</hi> above a <hi>Priest,</hi> to be found in the <hi>New Testament,</hi> and allow'd unto a <hi>Priest</hi> the Power of <hi>Ordination,</hi> and of <hi>Excommunication.</hi> In the very first Year of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's Reign, there was an <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> which
<note n="(k)" place="margin">Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> VI. p. 51.</note> as <hi>Heylin</hi> complains, forced the <hi>Episcopal Order</hi> from their strong hold of <hi>Divine Institution,</hi> and made them no other than the <hi>King's Ministers only.</hi> Dr. <hi>Poinet,</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> then writing against <hi>Gardiner,</hi> shews, That the <hi>Reformers</hi> in those Days, were willing even to lay aside the Name of <hi>Bishop,</hi> and say <hi>Elder</hi> instead of it. And the incomparable <hi>Cranmer</hi> in his Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions to the King's Questions, approved by other <hi>Bishops,</hi> has these express Words,
<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Resol.</hi> to <hi>Q.</hi> 10.</note>
               <hi>The Bishops and Priests were not two distinct things, but both one Office in the beginning of Christ's Religion;</hi> and he farther makes it manifest, that the great Reformers owned not <hi>Episcopacy</hi> as a <hi>distinct Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> from <hi>Presbytery</hi> to be of <hi>Divine Right,</hi> but only as a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95457:9"/>prudent constitution of the <hi>Magistrate</hi> for the better gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Church. Beacon</hi> also, a famous Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugee in Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s time, in his <hi>Catechism,</hi> dedicated to both <hi>Archbishops,</hi> puts the Question, <hi>What difference is there between a Bishop and a Presbyter?</hi> And answers, <hi>None at all; their Office is the same, their Authority and Power is one.</hi> Upon the revival of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> at <hi>Q. Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s coming to the Crown, the most acknowledged and celebrated Writers of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> still made the very same Concession. Dr. <hi>Alley,</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> in his <hi>Miscellanea,</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Alley</hi>'s <hi>Poor Man's Library.</hi> Tom. 1. p. 95, 96.</note> proves, both from the <hi>Acts of the Apostles,</hi> and from the <hi>Epistle to the Philippians,</hi> That the Scriptures make no difference between <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Elders;</hi> and he says, That before <hi>Factions,</hi> by the instinct of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, began in Religion, the Churches were governed with <hi>the Common Council of the Priests,</hi> or <hi>Elders.</hi> Dr. <hi>Pilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Duresme,</hi> in his <hi>Consutation</hi> of the <hi>Addition,</hi> affirms, That the Priviledges and Superiorities which <hi>Bishops</hi> have above other <hi>Ministers,</hi> be <hi>rather granted by Man for maintaining of Quietness in the Commonwealth, than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God in his Word.</hi> The rare Dr. <hi>Whitaker,</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Regim.</hi> cont. 4. q. 1. §. 29. p. 540. col. 2.</note> making his Remarks on <hi>Jerom</hi>'s Confession, That the <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> between <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Bishops,</hi> was brought in by <hi>Men</hi> long after the <hi>Apostles,</hi> as a Remedy against <hi>Schism;</hi> assures us, <hi>That it is a Remedy worse than the Malady.</hi> And Bishop <hi>Morton</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apol. Cathol.</hi> l. 1. c. 21. p. 55.</note> tells the Papists, That the Power of <hi>Order</hi> and of <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> which they ascribe to <hi>Bishops,</hi> doth <hi>De Jure Divino,</hi> belong to all other <hi>Presbyters.</hi> But, that I may supersede a vast Number of other Quotations to this purpose, let it suffice, That the Excellent Bishop <hi>Jewel</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers this not as his private Opinion, but as the sense of the <hi>Church of England:</hi>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apol.</hi> Part 2. ch. 3. Div. 5.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">In Saint <hi>Jerom</hi>'s time, (saith he,) there were <hi>Metropolitans, Arch-Bishops, and Arch-Deacons,</hi> and others; but Christ appointed not these <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions</hi> of <hi>Orders</hi> from the Beginning. This is the thing which we defend. St. <hi>Jerom</hi> saith, <hi>Let Bishops under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that they are in Authority over Priests, more by custom than by order of God's Truth. Erasmus</hi> speaking of the Times of <hi>Jerom,</hi> saith, <hi>Id temporis idem crat Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, Sacerdos &amp; Presbyter;</hi> these three Names, <hi>Bishops,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95457:9"/>Priest,</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> at that time were all one; and unto this Testimony of <hi>Jerom,</hi> the <hi>Bishop</hi> adds that of St. <hi>Austin,</hi> That the Office of a <hi>Bishop</hi> is above the Office of a <hi>Priest,</hi> not by Authority of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> but after the Names of <hi>Honour,</hi> which the <hi>Custom</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> hath now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</q> Yea, Archbishop <hi>Whitgift</hi> himself, speaking of the Government of the <hi>Church of England</hi> by <hi>Bishops,</hi> in his time,
<note n="(q)" place="margin">Tract. 17. ch. 2. Dio. 29.</note> says, <q rend="margQuotes">It is well known, that the Manner and Form of <hi>Government</hi> used in the <hi>Apostles Time,</hi> and expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> is <hi>not now observed;</hi> but hath of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity been altered; and that any one kind of <hi>external Government</hi> perpetually to be observed, is no where in the <hi>Scripture</hi> prescribed unto the Church, but the Charge thereof is left unto the <hi>Magistrate. Neither do I know</hi> (saith he,) <hi>any Learned Man of a contrary Judgment.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>You see, Sirs, that <hi>Cranmer</hi> and <hi>Jewel,</hi> and the Chief of the <hi>Reformers,</hi> are as good as <hi>Excommunicated</hi> by the <hi>New Church of England;</hi> but <hi>you</hi> will, I know, readily receive them into your Communion, and may now in this Point value your selves, as being of the same <hi>Church of England</hi> with <hi>them.</hi> Indeed very few of the <hi>Bishops</hi> themselves as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted any other than what <hi>you</hi> assert about this matter, until all things were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be put into the hands of a <hi>Party,</hi> that in pursuance of certain <hi>secret Articles,</hi> were to effect an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation with <hi>Rome;</hi> and then by the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of <hi>Prclacy,</hi> the Power of <hi>Opposition</hi> must be taken out of the hands of the <hi>Inferiour Clergy,</hi> who generally abhorred that <hi>vile Design.</hi> But it hath ever since been growing upon the Nation:
<note n="(*)" place="margin">See Def. of Mr. <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Schism,</hi> p. 35.</note> Tho' I am informed the present Learned Bishop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> hath learnedly and couragiously ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared on <hi>your</hi> side against it.
<note n="(†)" place="margin">Vind. of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> p. 306.</note> We will then pass to another <hi>Article, viz.</hi> That of your DISCIPLINE, which is too severe a thing to be allowed by some that would be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, if you should not allow <hi>them</hi> to be the only <hi>Church of England.</hi> It will doubtless be as great a <hi>Satisfaction</hi> as <hi>Vindication,</hi> for you to find the <hi>True Church of England</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving and applauding that very <hi>Discipline</hi> which is in <hi>your</hi> Churches practised: Now we all know what the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> requires of all its <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Examine your Lives and Conversations by the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95457:10"/>Rule of God's Commandment, [These are the express Words in the <hi>Order for the Administration of the Lord's Supper:</hi>] And whereinsoever ye shall perceive your selves to have offended, either by Will, Word, or Deed, bewail your own sinfulness, and confess your selves to Almighty God, with full purpose of amendment of Life. And if ye shall perceive your Offences to be such as are not only against God, but also against your Neighbours, then ye shall recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile your selves unto them. If any of you be a Blasphemer of God, an Hinderer, or Slanderer of his Word, an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, or be in Malice, or Envy, or any other grievous Crime, repent you of your Sins, or else come not unto that Holy Table, lest after the taking of that Holy Sacrament, the <hi>Devil</hi> enter into you as he entred into <hi>Judas,</hi> and <hi>bring you to Destruction both of Body and Soul.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> all the <hi>strictness</hi> used in your Churches about the <hi>Terms</hi> and <hi>Ways</hi> of admission to the <hi>Lord's Table</hi> with you, is nothing more nor less but a <hi>Trial</hi> of your <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants,</hi> whether they have those Qualifications which the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> hath prescribed. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in some of your <hi>Churches</hi> the <hi>Candidates</hi> of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion have not their <hi>Admission,</hi> without certain <hi>Publick Circumstances</hi> of expressing their consent unto the <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> But this is no more than what I find the more pious Divines in the <hi>Church of England</hi> wishing and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for. And one of them not Seven Years ago, hath pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished his Mind in these Terms:
<note n="(r)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Snoden</hi>'s Plea for Abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, p. 41.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Would it not very much conduce to the Honour of God, and the Edification of the People, in their most holy Faith, if every Person baptized into the Christian Faith, should be obliged, when he comes to Years of Discretion, to appear in the Publick Congregation, there to make a <hi>Confession of his Faith,</hi> to recognize his Primitive Engagement, to avow that in his own <hi>Person</hi> which was done for him by <hi>Proxy;</hi> and that the Minister of the Congregation should recommend the Person to the Grace of God.</q> I durst say, that the strict Churches of <hi>New-England</hi> it self, which wisely chuse to be as <hi>explicite</hi> as may be, in managing their <hi>Church-matters,</hi> do not ask for any thing more than what this Learned Son of the <hi>Church of England</hi> has thus propounded. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95457:10"/>
               <hi>you</hi> are for maintaining a <hi>Godly Discipline</hi> in your Churches towards those who scandalously break the Laws of our Lord Jesus Christ, is <hi>this</hi> any more than the very <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> has encouraged? You know that the first Words of the <hi>Commination against Sinners</hi> in that Book, are these: <q rend="margQuotes">Brethren, in the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> there was a <hi>Godly Discipline,</hi> that such Persons as stood Convicted of notorious Sin, were put unto <hi>open Penance;</hi> — instead whereof, until the said <hi>Discipline</hi> may be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored again, which is much to be wished,</hi> it is thought good that at this time should be read the General Sentences of God's Cursing against impenitent Sinners.</q> Now, I hope, you will not be denied your being a part of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> meerly because you have actually <hi>Restored</hi> that which the <hi>Church of England</hi> advises us, <hi>It were much to be wished</hi> that it might be <hi>restored.</hi> I believe the Churches of <hi>New-England</hi> it self, in their <hi>Plat-form of Church Discipline,</hi> have not a more severe Passage than that in the <hi>Homilies</hi> of the <hi>Church of England:</hi>
               <note n="(s)" place="margin">The Second Part of the <hi>Homily</hi> of <hi>The Right use of the Church.</hi>
               </note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">According to the Example of our Saviour Christ, and the Primitive Church, which was most holy and godly, and in the which <hi>due Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> with severity was against the wicked, open Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, were not admitted unto the use of the Holy <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> with other true Christians, until they had done open Penance before the whole Church: And this was practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed not only upon <hi>mean</hi> Persons, but also upon the Rich, Noble, and Mighty.</q> Behold, Sirs, <hi>your Discipline</hi> is by the <hi>Church of England</hi> it self, called, <hi>A due Discipline.</hi> The <hi>Church of England</hi> having thus allowed your <hi>Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> I hope now a few CEREMONIES, which by its own confession were never <hi>Instituted</hi> by the Lord Jesus Christ, will never be counted so <hi>Essential</hi> to it, that for the <hi>want thereof</hi> you must be cast out of doors. Believe it, Sirs, an <hi>House</hi> built meerly upon <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> or Parts and Means of <hi>Worship,</hi> not <hi>Instituted</hi> in the <hi>Sayings of our Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> will doubtless one Day suffer a <hi>Storm</hi> wherein it will <hi>Fall, and great will be the Fall of it.</hi> But that for your aversion to the <hi>Uninstituted Ceremonies,</hi> you may have as clear a Direction from the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> as may be, I desire to be informed, Whether the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95457:11"/>of Faith</hi> in an hundred Articles on the <hi>Creed,</hi> compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by Dr. <hi>Hooper,</hi> the excellent Bishop of <hi>Glocester,</hi> were not <hi>then</hi> agreeable to the sense of the <hi>Church?</hi> Now in the <hi>Eighty-fifth</hi> of these Articles there is this remarkable Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage: <q rend="margQuotes">They are not only <hi>Idolaters</hi> which worship and serve <hi>Idols,</hi> and <hi>strange Gods,</hi> as the <hi>Ethnicks,</hi> and such like, but also all those that worship and serve the true God of Heaven, <hi>after their own Fantasie,</hi> or <hi>after the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Men,</hi> without Faith, without the Word of God, and <hi>otherwise than God hath commanded them.</hi>
               </q> This is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a <hi>terrible Passage;</hi> and it is the Terrour of what is in it, that hath made <hi>you</hi> to be what you are: But it is none of <hi>you,</hi> 'tis a very Reverend Bishop of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> that hath written it; and in the same <hi>Confession</hi> hath he also written, <q rend="margQuotes">That upon pain of <hi>deadly Sin,</hi> to forbid and command things that indeed are but <hi>Indifferent,</hi> is the only Note and Mark by which to know <hi>Antichrist.</hi>
               </q> Our more conformable Friends in the <hi>Church of England</hi> hear not <hi>you</hi> calling them <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and yet <hi>they,</hi> as well as <hi>you,</hi> will own, That the <hi>Surplice</hi> made an Appurtenance of Divine Worship, the <hi>Cross</hi> in <hi>Baptism,</hi> and <hi>Kneeling</hi> before the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist,</hi> and the like, are things introduced in the <hi>Service of the true God of Heaven, after their own Fantasie, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Traditions of Men, and without the Word of God, and otherwise than God hath Commanded.</hi> If therefore you decline such things, the <hi>Church of England</hi> will certainly excuse you, while you have the <hi>Confession of Faith</hi> publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by its own <hi>Bishops,</hi> thus charming you so to do; espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially since there are of the <hi>Bishops</hi> Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> for one, who acknowledged, That the <hi>Sign of the Cross,</hi> as now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, is a <hi>Part of external Worship,</hi> tho' it be an <hi>Unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted Ceremony.</hi> The <hi>Church of England,</hi> with all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants,</hi> will grant you, That all <hi>Worship</hi> of God, not <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,</hi> is <hi>unlawful;</hi> and that no <hi>Power on Earth</hi> can add any thing to the <hi>Worship</hi> of God. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to <hi>Prot. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciler,</hi> p. 56.</note> himself will grant you, <q rend="margQuotes">That such <hi>significant Ceremonies</hi> as are meerly for <hi>Signification</hi> in the Christian Religion, do on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>obscure</hi> and <hi>debase,</hi> and are only fit for the Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Children.</hi>
               </q> And <hi>you,</hi> finding that the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> now used by the Conformable in the <hi>Church of England,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95457:11"/>are used and urged as <hi>direct Expressions</hi> of the reverence of the Heart unto God, cannot look on them as any other than <hi>Parts of external Worship,</hi> the <hi>Invention</hi> whereof is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the <hi>Second Commandment.</hi> Now, if you are delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the <hi>Yoke</hi> of these unhappy <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> I know not why you should thereby come to be by the <hi>Church of England</hi> worse looked upon than the most famous Divines of that <hi>Church,</hi> who in their best Writings are still groaning for a <hi>Deliverance.</hi> Will the <hi>Church of England</hi> renounce Bishop <hi>Bilson</hi> for saying, <q rend="margQuotes">That the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> are so far from admitting the <hi>full Dose</hi> of the Heresies of the <hi>Papists,</hi> that by no means they can digest a <hi>Dram</hi> of <hi>their Ceremonies?</hi> Will they renounce Dr. <hi>Humphrey,</hi> for saying, That we ought to refuse to conform unto the Enemies of God in any of their <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and that he wished and hoped for the utter abolishing of all the Monuments of Popish Superstition which yet remain in our Church? Will they renounce Dr. <hi>More</hi> for saying, That, <q rend="margQuotes">It is an <hi>Antichristian</hi> use of Church-Government, to direct it unto the upholding of <hi>Scandalous Ceremonies,</hi> and the ensna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Inventions of Men?</q>
               </q> A thousand more such Passages occur in the Writings of the Divines, who have all along been reputed the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">See a Collection in <hi>Delaun</hi>'s Plea for the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists.</note> Will the Church now renounce these Divines? Let them! And <hi>you,</hi> my Brethren, I am confident, will be glad of their Company. But I suppose there is another thing that a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle stumbles you; and that is this: If <hi>Conformity</hi> to the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> be necessary to render one a <hi>Church of England Man,</hi> why should not <hi>Non-conformity</hi> exclude <hi>one</hi> as well as another from that Character? <hi>Supra-conformity</hi> is no less <hi>Non-conformity</hi> than <hi>Subter-conformity.</hi> Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes in <hi>England</hi> continually <hi>Go beyond</hi> the Rule of <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> why should not these be <hi>Non-conformists</hi> as well as they that <hi>fall short</hi> of it? It is Enacted, <q rend="margQuotes">That no Form or Order of Common-Prayer, Administration of Sacraments, Rites, Ceremonies, shall be openly used in any Church, Chapel, or other publick Place, of or in any Colledge or Hall, in either of the Universities, the Colledges of <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster, Winchester,</hi> or <hi>Eaton,</hi> or any of them, other than what is prescribed and appointed to be used in and by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95457:12"/>the Book of <hi>Common Prayer.</hi>
               </q> Now in that Book, there are no where found several <hi>Ceremonies</hi> now practised, nor <hi>Orders</hi> used in many of the <hi>publick Churches. Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> being indeed nothing but a varying from the Rule established; the <hi>Addition</hi> made by some to that Rule, one would think should be <hi>Non-conformity,</hi> as well as the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straction</hi> made by others: And the Churches that perform the Worship of Christ with <hi>Organs</hi> be <hi>Non-conformists</hi> as well as they that omit the <hi>Cross,</hi> and some other Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities. I'll only touch upon this <hi>One Instance</hi> instead of many; the <hi>Rubrick</hi> requires, That the <hi>Communion-Table</hi> shall stand in the <hi>Body of the Church,</hi> or in the <hi>Chancel,</hi> and the <hi>Priest shall stand at the North-side of the Table;</hi> so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it a <hi>Table</hi> according to the other Churches of the <hi>Reformation;</hi> (which accordingly they observe in the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> where the <hi>Law</hi> is best understood and practised;) and yet in opposition to Authority in most places, they set it <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> clapping it unto the Wall at the <hi>East-end</hi> of the Church, with <hi>Rails</hi> before it, as if (according to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>) it were an <hi>Altar.</hi> This is <hi>contrary to the Law;</hi> and I have read, <q rend="margQuotes">This one thing may well be thought for to have given Encouragement unto the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists</hi> in some other cases.</q> Briefly, If you must be <hi>no Part</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> because you don't <hi>kneel</hi> at the <hi>Communion,</hi> I pray let the <hi>Priest</hi> who does not <hi>stand</hi> where by the Law of <hi>Conformity</hi> he ought to <hi>stand</hi> at the <hi>Communion,</hi> be discarded also! Tho' furious Bigots for <hi>Conformity</hi> will give no Answer but <hi>Railing</hi> to all of this <hi>Reason;</hi> yet <hi>you, my Brethren,</hi> will calmly afford a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable Attention to it. But you must by the way be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed withal to cease <hi>wondring</hi> at such <hi>Contradictions.</hi> If they seem wonderful to you, you'll find continual Matter of Wonderment: For instance, The Scripture commands us, <hi>Be not forgetful to entertain Strangers;</hi> but the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> contradicts it, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 11.34. dissuading us from <hi>Receiving a Stranger into our House.</hi> The Scripture commands us, <hi>Love your Enemies, do good to them that hate you; be like your heavenly Father, who makes the Sun to rise upon the evil and the good;</hi> but the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> contradicts it, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.4, 7. <hi>Give to the godly Man, and help not a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95457:12"/>Sinner;</hi> and again, <hi>Give to the Good, and help not the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> No Argument could prevail with our <hi>Unreformables</hi> to expunge these Lessons; but in the Month of <hi>October</hi> these Lessons of the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> must be read as the <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the <hi>Church of England:</hi> And then you must subscribe, That <hi>nothing is ordained to be read, but the very pure Words of God, or that which is agreeable to them.</hi> An a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of such <hi>Contradictions</hi> will accost you, in <hi>that</hi> which with a <hi>Contradiction</hi> equal to the rest, would be call'd, <hi>The only Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be now objected against <hi>you,</hi> That the <hi>Dislike of the</hi> COMMON-PRAYER is a thing that will utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar you from any Part in the <hi>Church of England;</hi> it will be no Defence for you to plead, That Old King <hi>James</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, a great Patron to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> called the <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> An <hi>ill-said Mass in English;</hi> for he was yet with the <hi>Kirk of Scotland</hi> when he so called it. But you may defend your selves by this, That several <hi>Bishops</hi> in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> namely, <hi>Williams, Prideaux, Brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig, Hacket,</hi> with Arch-Bishop <hi>Usher</hi> in the Head of them, disliked the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> so much, as to present unto the English Parliament no less than <hi>Thirty-five</hi> Exceptions against several things in it, calling for a <hi>Reformation.</hi> If <hi>their Exceptions</hi> did not forfeit their Claim to be of the <hi>Church,</hi> why should <hi>yours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps they'll complain of you, That you do not use the LORD's PRAYER as a <hi>Form.</hi> If they do, you may stop the Complaint, by citing to them not only an Army of the <hi>Ancients,</hi> but one who has been a great Oracle to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> even <hi>Grotius</hi> himself, declaring, That our <hi>Lord bound not his Disciples to the use of those Words and Syllables.</hi> If he <hi>did,</hi> why does the <hi>Church of England</hi> it self presume to <hi>alter</hi> them? In the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> the Form still is, <hi>Forgive us our Trespasses as we forgive them that Trespass against us.</hi> The <hi>Church of England</hi> herein varies from the Words of our Lord Jesus Christ: In <hi>Matthew</hi> his Words are, <hi>Forgive us our Debts as we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give our Debtors:</hi> In <hi>Luke</hi> his Words are, <hi>Forgive us our Sins, for we forgive every one that is indebted unto us.</hi> Why must <hi>you</hi> be tyed unto a <hi>Form</hi> of Words? The <hi>Church
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95457:13"/>of England,</hi> even when most pretending to a <hi>Form,</hi> will not be tyed, even to <hi>That</hi> for which there is the most pretence. The <hi>Infatuation</hi> discovered by the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> thus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the Form and Phrase of the <hi>Lord</hi>'s-<hi>Prayer,</hi> deserves to be considered! It may be, when you have silenced some of these froward <hi>Children</hi> in <hi>Christianity,</hi> from insisting on all their other <hi>Impertinencies,</hi> they will still refuse to visit <hi>your</hi> Assemblies, because the <hi>Houses</hi> wherein you hold them, are not so Fine and Gay as many of <hi>their</hi> publick Churches. But you may presently shew them, That the <hi>Gaudy Trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings</hi> bestow'd on some of <hi>their Churches</hi> are directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>Church of England.</hi> For the <hi>Homily</hi> against the <hi>Peril of Idolatry,</hi> expresly declares against the Abuses of <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Temples,</hi> by too <hi>costly</hi> and <hi>sumptuous</hi> decking and adorning of them.
<note n="(w)" place="margin">The Third Part of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>the Peril of Idolatry.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>These and such Points might be improved much more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to demonstrate, That <hi>you</hi> are indeed among the TRUEST SONS of the <hi>True Church</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> But what needs any more, since 'tis a Maxim, (and there is no need of quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Avicen</hi> for the Maxim,) <hi>Quicquid sufficientiae additur, superfluitati ascribitur?</hi> All that you will now demand of me, is to describe clearly and fairly to you, <hi>What is that</hi> NEW CHURCH <hi>of England</hi> whereto you do <hi>not</hi> belong, and I suppose, are not very willing to belong? 'Tis very certain, there is a <hi>Party</hi> in the <hi>English Nation</hi> usurping the Name of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> whereto it will be as <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> your <hi>Honour</hi> as 'tis your <hi>Desire</hi> to be <hi>United;</hi> and which (as one says) differs as much from the OLD CHURCH <hi>of England,</hi> as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> grazing among <hi>Beasts</hi> in the Field, from <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> sitting on his glittering <hi>Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know then, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> That by a prevailing Faction in <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Canon Law</hi> which pretends to Form the <hi>Church of England,</hi> hath been more than once altered, since the Family of the <hi>Stewarts</hi> came to sit on the Throne of Great <hi>Britain;</hi> and the Alteration hath now made a <hi>New Church</hi> in <hi>England</hi> of quite another kind, than what was before. There is now established by Law a <hi>National Church,</hi> which the <hi>Canons</hi> do (tho' Arch-Bishop <hi>Whitgift</hi> a little before durst <hi>not,</hi>) affirm to be a <hi>True and Apostolical
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95457:13"/>Church.</hi> The <hi>Bishops,</hi> which before <hi>then,</hi> durst as well have eaten Fire as have pretended to be as <hi>Diocesan Bishops,</hi> any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the <hi>King's Officers,</hi> do by the <hi>Canons</hi> now lay claim unto a <hi>Divine Right.</hi> But because it puzzles them to make the <hi>King,</hi> who is not a Person <hi>in Orders,</hi> the <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> having these <hi>Officers</hi> under him, and yet for to make the <hi>Arch-Bishop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the <hi>Head</hi> of the Church, is <hi>Treason; here</hi> they are in <hi>Confusion:</hi> And I suppose, you <hi>my Brethren,</hi> will not ask to be of <hi>this Church</hi> till you see them extricated out of this <hi>Confusion.</hi> To proceed, In the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church</hi> thus established, there are <hi>Twenty-six Diocesses,</hi> which the <hi>Canons</hi> make <hi>particular Churches</hi> of the lowest Rank; and tho' there be such vast numbers of <hi>Parishes</hi> in these <hi>Diocesses,</hi> the <hi>Canons</hi> have utterly divested them of the Character of <hi>particular Churches,</hi> which once they had some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of, and they make no more than <hi>Twenty-six Churches,</hi> and no more than <hi>Twenty-six Pastors</hi> in the whole Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Parish-Presbyters</hi> are by the <hi>Canons</hi> alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether stripp'd of all Power to <hi>Ordain,</hi> or to <hi>Confirm,</hi> or to <hi>Excommunicate;</hi> tho' once there was a <hi>Power of Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> conceded unto <hi>them,</hi> which then made the Old <hi>Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists</hi> to look on the <hi>Parish-Ministers</hi> as <hi>Pastors,</hi> and the <hi>Parishes</hi> as retaining the Substantials of <hi>particular Churches.</hi> You, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> have been ready to say with Dr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">In some of the Parishes of the Kingdom, there are many god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men that constantly give up themselves unto the Worship of God in publick, and meet together in one place, to that end, in a constant way, under a godly Ministry whom they themselves have chosen to cleave unto, (tho' they did not chuse him at first;) these, notwithstanding their mixture and want of Discipline, I never thought, for my part, but they were <hi>true Churches of Christ.</hi>
               </q> But now the <hi>Diocesan Church-Government</hi> being by <hi>Canon</hi> established, the <hi>Parishes</hi> are no more allow'd any of them to be <hi>particular Churches.</hi> Arch-Bishop <hi>Laud</hi> labouring for a full Settlement of this New Church-State, <hi>perished in the way:</hi> But upon the Restaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. the Labours of the <hi>New Set,</hi> for to obtain <hi>Laud</hi>'s Model, found more success. In those places of the <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> where they found the Word <hi>[Pastor,]</hi> they blotted it out, and put in <hi>Priest,</hi> or <hi>Curate.</hi> And in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95457:14"/>New Book of <hi>Ordering Bishops, Priests,</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> not only the <hi>Execution</hi> of the <hi>Office,</hi> but the very <hi>Office</hi> of a <hi>Priest</hi> is taken away from all that have not <hi>Episcopal Ordination.</hi> The <hi>Epistles</hi> and <hi>Gospels</hi> to be formerly read at the <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Priests,</hi> which referred unto the <hi>Pastoral Office,</hi> are now to be read only at the <hi>Consecration</hi> of a <hi>Bishop.</hi> All <hi>Presbyterian Ordinations</hi> were declared null and void by the memorable <hi>Act of Uniformity,</hi> and they that had <hi>no more</hi> were pronounced as <hi>naturally Dead.</hi> This <hi>Diocesan</hi> Church of <hi>England,</hi> according to <hi>Canon,</hi> receives to <hi>Baptism</hi> the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of all <hi>Parents,</hi> (be they <hi>Jewish</hi> or <hi>Pagan</hi>) that are brought unto the Minister. And every <hi>Baptized Inhabitant</hi> within the <hi>Diocess,</hi> if he be not <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> or doth say, That he heartily desires the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> is admitted unto that Sacrament also, if he will take it according to the <hi>Form</hi> in the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> (by the common Custom of the Church,) altho' he be never so ungodly. Whatever Admonitions the <hi>Rubric</hi> or <hi>Canons</hi> do give against admitting the <hi>Wicked</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> 'tis yet abundantly provided in them, That the <hi>Administrator</hi> shall be uncapable of excluding the wickedest alive. But at the same time,
<note n="(x)" place="margin">See <hi>Can.</hi> 27.</note> all those who <hi>refuse to Kneel at the reception of the Sacrament,</hi> or who <hi>refuse to be Present at Publick Prayers, according to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>which Orders be,</hi>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">See <hi>Can.</hi> 18.</note>
               <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently to Kneel, when the General Confession, Litany, and other Prayers are read, and Stand up at the saying of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and Bow at the Name of Jesus, and Say in their due place, and audibly with the Minister, the Confession, the Lord's Prayer, and the Creed, and make such other Answers to the Publick Prayers as are appointed in the Book of Common-Prayer; all such as refuse to do any of these things, are to be denied the Communion; and what Minister soever shall wittingly admit them, he is liable to Suspension.</hi> Yea, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever affirms, That the <hi>Church of England, as by Law thus established,</hi> is not formed according to Divine Institution, (or <hi>Apostolical,</hi>) is <hi>ipso facto</hi> to be looked upon as <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">See <hi>Can.</hi> 3, 4, 6, 7.</note> This is the <hi>Roaring</hi> of the Ecclesiastical <hi>Canons,</hi> and the <hi>Clergy</hi> by their Oath of <hi>Canonical Obedience,</hi> are sworn to observe these as well as the rest of the <hi>Canons. My Brethren,</hi> while you belong to the CHRISTIAN CHURCH
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95457:14"/>OF ENGLAND, you have all the reason imaginable to hear it, and bear it, and own it patiently, if you be told that you do not belong unto this DIOCESAN CHURCH OF ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND. For, <hi>First,</hi> If I be not mistaken, this presumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous CANONICAL CHURCH OF ENGLAND has <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated</hi> the best of <hi>Princes,</hi> (notwithstanding its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Loyalty,</hi>) if they do but offer to contest any Part of its Constitution; and it will be no dishonour unto <hi>you</hi> to be partakers with such illustrious Heads, in suffering these <hi>Contradictions of Sinners.</hi> Perhaps you'll be surprized at this; but if any <hi>Princes</hi> or <hi>Parliaments,</hi> who declare, That they who cannot use the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> may be Men of a very <hi>good Conscience,</hi> escape an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication</hi> by the <hi>Sixth Canon</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> which is, <hi>Whosoever shall hereafter affirm, That the Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church of</hi> England <hi>by Law established, are such as being commanded by lawful Authority, Men who are zealously and godlily affected, may not with any good Conscience approve them, use them, or subscribe unto them, let him be Excommunicated</hi> ipso facto: I doubt the <hi>Eighth Canon</hi> bears too hard upon them. According to that, <hi>Whosoever shall hereafter affirm or teach, That the Form and Manner of making and consecrating Bishops, Priests, or Deacons, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth any thing in it that is repugnant unto the Word of God, let them be Excommunicated</hi> ipso facto, <hi>and not be restor'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he repent, and publickly revoke such his wicked Errour.</hi> That <hi>Form</hi> does assert, That <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Priests</hi> are distinct Orders in <hi>Christ's Church;</hi> and that it is <hi>evident unto all Men diligently reading Holy Scripture,</hi> that from the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles time</hi> they have been so. Now suppose any <hi>Princes</hi> give the <hi>Royal Assent</hi> unto an <hi>Act</hi> for the extirpation of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops</hi> in one of the Three <hi>Kingdoms;</hi> have they not very em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically <hi>taught</hi> us, That this Assertion in the <hi>Form of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrating Bishops and Priests,</hi> is not according to the <hi>Word of God?</hi> Have they not very sufficiently affirmed, That the <hi>Word of God</hi> obliges us not for to acknowledge <hi>Bishops</hi> of an <hi>Order distinct</hi> from other <hi>Ministers</hi> in the <hi>Church of Christ?</hi> We'll suppose they have somewhere or other in express Terms,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">They are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press Words of the <hi>Act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolishing Prelacy,</hi> July 5. 1689.</note>
               <hi>abolished Prelacy and Superiority in any Office in the Church above Presbyters;</hi> and declared and ordained the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95457:15"/>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">The <hi>Act resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery,</hi> July 25. 1689.</note>
               <hi>Government of the Church</hi> there, by <hi>Presbyters without Bishops, to be the only true and proper Government thereof.</hi> I am certain, this is to proclaim it with a witness, That <hi>the Superiority of Bishops, as an Order above Presbyters, is not Instituted in the Word of God.</hi> And at the same time it is to maintain, <hi>That the Doctrine of the Form of making Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops and Priests, which asserts that Superiority of Order to be of Divine Right, is repugnant unto the Word of God.</hi> These <hi>Princes</hi> it seems, (which indeed I abhor to mention) stand excommunicated <hi>ipso facto,</hi> by the <hi>Eighth</hi> Canon of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> until they <hi>repent and publickly revoke the wicked Errours</hi> committed in abolishing that <hi>Prelacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This CANONICAL CHURCH continuing to offer such Affronts unto Majesty, you may well decline to be any Part of it, until they <hi>repent and publickly revoke their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Canons.</hi> But that which may confirm you in this aversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that <hi>Church,</hi> is the wrong which those <hi>Canons</hi> do to all the <hi>Ministers</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ in the World. For ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>them,</hi> none of the <hi>Scotch,</hi> or <hi>Dutch,</hi> or <hi>French Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters,</hi> nor any of <hi>your own,</hi> are <hi>true Ministers</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ, while they want <hi>Episcopal Ordination.</hi> Albeit, the famous Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> has out of <hi>Eutychius</hi> proved, That not only <hi>Bishops,</hi> but <hi>Patriarchs</hi> themselves, were in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Times <hi>Ordained</hi> by <hi>Presbyters;</hi> yet now, forsooth, according to our <hi>New Church,</hi> none may be owned for so much as <hi>Presbyters,</hi> but such as have been <hi>Ordained</hi> by <hi>Diocesan Bishops.</hi> And therefore, altho' this <hi>Canonical Church</hi> will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a <hi>Popish Priest</hi> upon his <hi>Abjuration,</hi> to be a Minister without <hi>Re-ordination,</hi> it will not without <hi>Re-ordination,</hi> admit any of these who are the best of <hi>Protestants.</hi> Yea, and when this <hi>Church</hi> has admitted any unto its <hi>Ministry,</hi> it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently strips them of the <hi>Rights</hi> that are essential to all <hi>true Ministers</hi> of the Lord Jesus Christ. And here I will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist on this, That by the <hi>Canons</hi> of this <hi>Church,</hi> its own Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters have not so much as liberty for one <hi>Occasional Prayer</hi> of their own left unto them. All the <hi>Conformists</hi> are by the <hi>Thirty-sixth Canon</hi> to subscribe <hi>ex animo,</hi> a <hi>Covenant,</hi> That <hi>they will use the Form in the Book of Common-Prayer, prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in Publick Prayer and Administration of the Sacraments, and</hi> NONE OTHER. Indeed a <hi>Custom</hi> for Ministers to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95457:15"/>
               <hi>pray without Book</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> is connived at; but in as much as they are <hi>Publick Prayers,</hi> I know others besides Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who doubt them to be a breach of the <hi>Canon-Covenant.</hi> I pass from this, to say, I suppose you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to acknowledge all the <hi>Parish-Presbyters</hi> faithfully feeding their willing Flocks in the Realm, notwithstanding their <hi>Conformity</hi> to be <hi>True Ministers</hi> of the Gospel; but their own <hi>Canons,</hi> even those to which they themselves have <hi>sworn,</hi> do all they can to forbid your doing so. For <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> too, must readily own, That unto the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a <hi>Minister</hi> of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> here are two things <hi>Essential,</hi> namely, <hi>Obligation</hi> to <hi>Teach,</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>Rule</hi> the Flock. Whereas the <hi>Canons,</hi> whatever they <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire</hi> in some <hi>Clauses,</hi> do evidently <hi>release</hi> the Parish-Minister from <hi>Obligation</hi> to <hi>Teach,</hi> by providing, <hi>That the Sacraments are not to be refused at the Hands of Unpreaching Ministers.</hi> And the whole <hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>Rule,</hi> is by the <hi>Canons</hi> reserved unto the <hi>Bishop,</hi> to be executed by his <hi>Lay-Chancellor;</hi> so that the <hi>Parish-Minister</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not exclude the veriest <hi>Infidel</hi> in the World from the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> if a certain <hi>Lay-Chancellor</hi> do order his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. Briefly, No Ordained <hi>Priest</hi> may take upon him, to Expound any <hi>Scripture,</hi> or <hi>Matter,</hi> or <hi>Doctrine,</hi> (or do any more than read) so much as to his own <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</hi> till he have a <hi>License</hi> from his <hi>Ordinary.</hi> And he <hi>then</hi> too has no more Power than any <hi>Lay-man</hi> to <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure</hi> an <hi>Offender,</hi> or to judge who are worthy to be <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured.</hi> Tho' the <hi>Rubric</hi> and <hi>Canon</hi> do seem sometimes to favour the <hi>Significancy</hi> of the <hi>Curates,</hi> yet elsewhere it the more inexcusably renders them utterly <hi>Insignificant.</hi> Doubtless you will wonder how that the <hi>Clergy</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves can with <hi>Patience</hi> endure to be so <hi>nullified,</hi> as they are by this their <hi>Canonical Church,</hi> or to see them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves more honoured by <hi>you</hi> that are <hi>Non-conformists</hi> than they are by their own <hi>Canons!</hi> But you are sensible what <hi>Force</hi> it is that obliges them unto their <hi>Patience.</hi> To see the <hi>Ministers</hi> of the Gospel so <hi>Degraded</hi> as they are by the <hi>Canons,</hi> gives Offence unto <hi>you,</hi> if not unto <hi>them;</hi> and methinks it should be no Offence unto <hi>them,</hi> that <hi>you</hi> take this Offence on <hi>their</hi> behalf.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:95457:16"/>
            <p>A Third Prejudice that you'll easily take up against this CANONICAL CHURCH, is the <hi>Number</hi> and <hi>Figure</hi> of those many other good Men, (besides <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,</hi>) whom they have <hi>Excommunicated.</hi> This <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicean Church</hi> may admire her own <hi>Charity,</hi> (that is to say, the <hi>Easiness</hi> of her <hi>Discipline</hi> as well as the <hi>Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of her <hi>Communion</hi> towards the worst of Men,) but she has the most <hi>Excommunicating</hi> and most <hi>Anathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Charity</hi> that ever was in the World. For by the <hi>Canons</hi> of that Church, <q rend="margQuotes">Whoever shall affirm,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">See <hi>Can.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note> That the <hi>Church of England</hi> by Law established, is not an <hi>Apostolical Church,</hi> or that its Worship is Corrupt, or that any of the 39 Articles are in any part Erroneous, or that the Rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> may not be used with a good Conscience, or that the Government of the Church by <hi>Arch-Bishops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, &amp;c.</hi> is repugnant to the Word of God, or that the <hi>Form or Manner of making or consecrating of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, Priests, and Deacons,</hi> containeth any thing in it repugnant to the Word of God, all these are to be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated <hi>ipso facto.</hi>
               </q> Now, Sirs, you'll find per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the bigger Part of the godly People in <hi>England,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven among the <hi>Conformists</hi> themselves, to be by one or other of these Clauses <hi>Excommunicated:</hi> That is to say, they are <hi>Excommunicated</hi> out of the CANONICAL CHURCH into the CHRISTIAN CHURCH OF ENGLAND: And I hope they will be content with their Condition, and not <hi>thrust</hi> themselves upon the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that has <hi>Excommunicated</hi> them. However, that <hi>you</hi> may be sure of being driven both <hi>out of,</hi> and <hi>into</hi> the same <hi>Church</hi> with <hi>them,</hi> hark how these <hi>Canons</hi> do fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Thunder!</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">See <hi>Can.</hi> 11.</note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Whosoever shall maintain, That there are within the <hi>Realm,</hi> [and Note by the way, That all the <hi>English</hi> Plantations, particularly <hi>Barbadoes, Jamaica, Bermudas, New-England, New-York, Virginia, Carolina,</hi> all which have <hi>Non-conformist Meetings</hi> in them, do belong to the <hi>Ecclesiastical Realm</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Part of the Bishop of <hi>London</hi>'s Diocess;] other Meetings, Assemblies, or Congregations of the King's<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95457:16"/>Subjects, than such as by the Law of the Land are held and allowed, which may rightly challenge to themselves the Name of <hi>true and lawful Churches,</hi> let them be <hi>Excommunicated,</hi> and not restored but by the <hi>Arch-Bishop,</hi> after Repentance and Publick Revocation of such <hi>their wicked Errours.</hi>
               </q> You see, Sirs, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you are that <hi>Church of England</hi> which the Law <hi>holds</hi> and <hi>allows,</hi> or else you stand <hi>Excommunicated.</hi> But I assure my self, you are not ambitious to be reckoned of that Party which has <hi>Excommunicated</hi> all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of the <hi>Non-conformists.</hi> Nor will it bring you under the Brand of <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> if being thus Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated <hi>ipso facto,</hi> you settle your selves in the Communion of <hi>Churches</hi> that will receive you. And this the rather, lest you should be found in the TREASONA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE PLOT, whereof the famous Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, has convicted that Party, namely, That of attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a <hi>Revolt unto a Foreign Jurisdiction.</hi> Albeit the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> of the Church, (and the <hi>Articles</hi> also,) whereto these Men are <hi>sworn,</hi> do most expresly renounce all such <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Jurisdiction;</hi> yet such is the <hi>Confusion</hi> whereinto these perfidious Builders of <hi>Babel</hi> run themselves, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>New Church of England,</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s true Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. <hi>p.</hi> 19. And his whole Book, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt unto a Foreign Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto the late A. B. of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </note>
               <q rend="margQuotes">The Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Bishops</hi> thro' all the World, are the Supream, Universal, Visible Sovereign of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> having power of <hi>Universal Government;</hi> That they are to exercise it in <hi>General Councils,</hi> where every Bishop is by Office the <hi>Representative</hi> of his <hi>Diocesan Church;</hi> That these Bishops are to have <hi>Metropolitans</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs,</hi> and the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> is to be their <hi>Uniting Head,</hi> and <hi>ex officio</hi> the President of the <hi>Councils;</hi> That in the Intervals of these <hi>Councils,</hi> they are <hi>per literas formatas,</hi> to exercise their Power over all the World; That all that will not unite with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> (which is to be distinguished from the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>) on these Terms, are <hi>Schismaticks;</hi> but they that <hi>will,</hi> are no <hi>Papists;</hi> none being <hi>Papists</hi> but they that are for the <hi>Pope's absolute Power</hi> above <hi>Canons</hi> or <hi>Councils;</hi> That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a <hi>true Church,</hi> and if it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95457:17"/>will not impose the <hi>Innovations</hi> of the last Four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years, it may be <hi>united</hi> with; but the <hi>Protestant Churches,</hi> which are destitute of <hi>Diocesan Bishops,</hi> are no true <hi>Churches,</hi> nor their Pastors true <hi>Ministers,</hi> nor have they any true <hi>Sacraments,</hi> nor Covenant-Promise of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Of such a Church as this, methinks I hear <hi>you,</hi> and the bigger and better Part of your Brethren, yet groaning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Shackles of <hi>Conformity,</hi> resolve, <hi>Come not into their Secret, O my Soul, unto their Assembly! my Tongue, be not thou united!</hi> The most flourishing and glorious <hi>Island</hi> in the World, will be in perpetual danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a <hi>French Province,</hi> except the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> be counted better Parts of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> than the Men of such <hi>dangerous Principles;</hi> and except the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental TEST be therefore taken off. But there is the True CHRISTIAN CHURCH of <hi>England,</hi> which would have the <hi>Reformation of Religion</hi> carried on accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Direction</hi> of the Sacred <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and the <hi>Intention</hi> of the first <hi>Reformers,</hi> and counts not <hi>Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> to lye in vain <hi>Ceremony;</hi> which looks on <hi>Diocesan Bishops</hi> as made such by the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>National Church-Government,</hi> as an <hi>human,</hi> tho' <hi>useful</hi> Policy; which owns the rest of the sound <hi>Protestants</hi> in the World for <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> and would have the Qualifications for the <hi>Pasto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Office,</hi> and for <hi>Communion</hi> in special Ordinances, to be no other than what the Lord Jesus Christ hath instituted; which, in fine, is against bringing a Yoke of <hi>Slavery</hi> upon the brave English Nation in <hi>Spirituals</hi> or <hi>Temporals.</hi> And <hi>of this Church ye are.</hi> God, and the King, and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and all sober Men, will reckon you a valuable Part of this <hi>Church;</hi> while a certain <hi>Hectoring</hi> sort of People in the World, that would be thought the only <hi>Church of England,</hi> deserve to be counted rather the <hi>Wens,</hi> than any <hi>Parts</hi> of it, and indeed <hi>know not what it is.</hi> I beseech you, Sirs, let not the CHURCH OF ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND become a Name of such a <hi>Treasonable Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> that it must belong to none but that Faction, whose Religion lyes in <hi>Sainting</hi> their Martyr <hi>Charles</hi> I.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95457:17"/>whose Reign was spent in an unnatural manner, plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and contriving to undermine and subvert the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Laws, and Liberties of the English Nation; and who notwithstanding the <hi>Sham</hi> of the <hi>Icon Basilike,</hi> it's feared would have been another <hi>John Basilovitz,</hi> if he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spered in his <hi>unnatural War</hi> against the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> if any go to seduce you from your own REFORMED CONGREGATIONS into the more CEREMONIOUS ASSEMBLIES in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> you are furnished with an <hi>Answer.</hi> Let your <hi>Answer</hi> be, That you are of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and that you cannot better express your being <hi>so,</hi> than by keeping with your own REFORMED CONGREGATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS. If the Bishop of <hi>London</hi> should be offended at the Governours of <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> or <hi>Bermudas,</hi> or <hi>Carolina,</hi> for worshipping of God in the Meetings of the <hi>Non-conformists</hi> there, the Gentlemen may truly say in their defence, That they worshipp'd God with the <hi>truest Part of the Church of England</hi> in those Parts of <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be advised, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> to carry it with all possible <hi>Moderation</hi> and <hi>Civility</hi> towards those that can <hi>Conform</hi> unto <hi>Ceremonies</hi> farther than <hi>you; Be gentle unto all Men.</hi> But yet continue stedfast in your present <hi>Non-conformity.</hi> The Day is at hand that will justifie your <hi>Stedfastness.</hi> Even at this Day, the most <hi>Conformable</hi> themselves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, That the <hi>Rites</hi> whereto you are <hi>Non-conformists,</hi> are <hi>indifferent Things,</hi> and the Worship of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ is as <hi>well</hi> without them as with them. Why should you then add those <hi>Rites,</hi> which in your <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi> are not so <hi>indifferent</hi> as the <hi>Confession</hi> of the <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable</hi> would render them, and which will defile your <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship?</hi> Even Bishop <hi>Sanderson</hi> himself expresly says, <hi>If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man shall use them with an opinion, as if God's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice could not be rightly performed without them, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less the use of such Ceremonies by reason of such his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, would be superstitious unto him.</hi> Thus by the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession</hi> of the <hi>Conformable,</hi> you are <hi>well</hi> as you <hi>are.</hi> Know when you are <hi>well.</hi> More <hi>Conformity</hi> won't make you <hi>better.</hi> And if the <hi>Rites</hi> are so <hi>Indifferent,</hi> why should
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95457:18"/>those that urge them for the sake thereof, make a <hi>Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence? Let them return unto you; there is no Cause why you should go over unto them. Reason</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> will one Day take place: The Day foretold by the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop</hi> of <hi>Worcester</hi> before he was a <hi>Bishop,</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">God will one Day convince Men, That the <hi>Unity</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> lyes more in the <hi>Unity</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Affection,</hi> than in the <hi>Uniformity</hi> of doubtful <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet</hi>'s <hi>Iren.</hi> p. 121.</note>.</q> You will then be owned in the <hi>Church of England;</hi> yea, the the <hi>Partition-Wall</hi> between <hi>you</hi> and all the other sincere <hi>Protestants</hi> in the <hi>English</hi> Nation, will be taken down. This is the Prayer and Hope of, <hi>my Brethren,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Hearty Servant,</hi> (<hi>Neither</hi> willing <hi>nor</hi> worthy <hi>to be any further known among you.</hi>) Philalethes.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:95457:18"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Tho. Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurst,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapside,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chapel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>EXpository Notes on the Four Evangelists; wherein the Sacred Text is at large recited, and the Sense explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; together with the Instructive Example of the Holy Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus is recommended to our Imitation. By <hi>William Burkitt,</hi> M. A. and Vicar of <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Essex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divine Comforts Antidoting inward Perplexities of Mind; being a Discourse upon <hi>Psalm.</hi> 94. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. By. <hi>T. Sharp,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Wilful Impenitency the grossest Self-Murder; in several Sermons Preached at <hi>Rochfort</hi> in <hi>Essex.</hi> By <hi>William Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <p>Plain Method of Catechising; shewing, That Ministers, Parents, and Masters, ought to be faithful Teachers of the first Principles of the Christian Doctrine. By <hi>T. Doolittle,</hi> M. A. in compassion to the Ignorant.</p>
            <p>The Young Man's Guide in his Way to Heaven; or, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling spiritualized.</p>
            <p>The General Assembly; or, the gathering of the Saints to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. By <hi>Oliver Heywood,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>The Order of the Gospel professed and practised by the Churches in <hi>New-England,</hi> in Answer to several Questions relating to Church-Discipline. By <hi>Increase Mather,</hi> Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of <hi>Harvard</hi> College in <hi>Cambridge, New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Primitia Synagogae;</hi> or, a Sermon Preached at the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a New Erected Meeting-house in <hi>Ipswich.</hi> By <hi>John Fairfax,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>The Fountain of Life opened and explained; or, a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play of Christ, in his Essential and Mediatorial Glory; containing Forty Two Sermons on various Texts. By <hi>John Flavel,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Of Thoughtfulness for the Morrow, with an Appendix concerning the immediate desire of foreknowing Things to come.</p>
            <p>The Redeemer's Tears wept over lost Souls, in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise
<pb facs="tcp:95457:19"/>on <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41, 42. with an Appendix, wherein some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what is occasionally Discoursed concerning the sin against the Holy Ghost, and how God is said to will the Salvation of them that perish.</p>
            <p>A Calm and Sober Enquiry concerning the possibility of a Trinity in the God-head, in a Letter to a Person of Worth; occasion'd by the lately Published Considerations on the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of the Doctrine of the Trinity. By Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> Dr. <hi>South,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cudworth, &amp;c.</hi> Together with certain Letters (hitherto unpublished) formerly written to the Reverend Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> on the same Subject.</p>
            <p>A Letter to a Friend concerning a Postscript to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Notion of the Trinity in Unity, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Calm Enquiry on the same Subject.</p>
            <p>A View of that part of the late considerations address'd to <hi>H. H.</hi> about the Trinity, which concerns the Sober En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry on that Subject.</p>
            <p>A Treatise of the Soul of Man, wherein the Divine Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, Excellent and Immortal Nature of the Soul, are opened; its Love and Inclination to the Body, with the necessity of its Separation from it, considered and improved. The Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence, Operations and States of separated Souls both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Hell immediately after Death, asserted, discussed, and variously applied. Divers knotty and difficult Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about departed Souls, both Philosophical and Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, stated and determined.</p>
            <p>The Method of Grace in bringing home the Eternal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, contrived by the Father and accomplished by the Son, thro' the Effectual Application of the Spirit unto God's Elect, being the Second Part of Gospel Redemption.</p>
            <p>The Divine Conduct or Mystery of Providence, its Being and Efficacy asserted and vindicated: All the Methods of Providence in our Course of Life open'd, with Directions how to apply and improve them.</p>
            <p>Navigation spiritualiz'd, or a new Compass for Seamen, consisting of Thirty Two Points of pleasant Observations, profitable Applications, serious Reflections, all concluded with so many spiritual Poems, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95457:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>